Guide to the Leonid Hurwicz papers, 1911-2008 and undated RL.00599
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Printed Materials Series, 1940s-2000s and undated, 22 boxes
  - Works by Others, 17 boxes
    - Topical Files, 1940s-2006 and undated, 51 boxes
      - Decentralization
        - Optimal Intertemporal Allocation Mechanisms & Decentralization of Decision, 1985 (Box 65)
      - Dimensional Requirements, 1974-1977 (Box 66)
      - Externalities
        - Handout for Warwick, 1962 (Box 66)
        - "Revisiting externalities," 1999 (Box 66)
      - Feiwel's interview, in relation with the works on general equilibrium with Arrow 1985 (Box 67)
      - Several drafts, proofs and corrections (Box 67)
      - Gauss (notes on) (Box 67)
      - Guesnerie, Roger (annotated papers) (Box 67)
      - Hammond, Peter (annotated papers) (Box 67)
      - Harsanyi, John (annotated papers) (Box 67)
      - Hotelling, Harold, notes on
        - Papers on Hotelling (Box 67)
        - Economics of Exhaustible Resources, 1931 (Box 67)
        - Comments on Hands and Mirowski's paper on Hotelling (Box 67)
      - Hotelling, Harold (Box 68)
        - Various notes, proofs and corrections by Hurwicz on Hands and Mirowski, 1996 (Box 68)
      - Integrability of Demand Functions, various notes, 1968-1969 (Box 68)
      - Irrational Societies, 1985-1988 (Box 68)
      - Lerner, Abba (notes on), incl.: controversy with Paul Samuelson 1959 (Box 68)
      - Lindbeck (annotated papers) (Box 68)
      - Machlup, Fritz, 1982 (Box 68)
      - Malinvaud (Box 68)
      - Majundar, M. (works by and with), 1980s (Box 69)
      - Marshak, Jacob, 1967-1969
        - Papers in honor of Marshak, some drafts (Box 69)
        - Mechanism design, book project (Box 69)
        - Letters and drafts in relation to a book published by Edna Leohman and Marc Kilgour, 1994-1997 (Box 69)
      - Thomas Marschak Files, 1950-2002, 9 boxes
        These papers document Hurwicz's works in relation with Thomas Marschak (no relation to Jacob Marshak). They contain drafts and notes on collaborative works as well as reprints of Marschak's works with annotations by Hurwicz. Most of their collaboration took place during the 1980s and dealt with mechanism design (dimensional requirements, resource allocations mechanisms). Arranged chronologically.
        - Works by Marschak, 1964-1981 (Box 70)
        - Various drafts and revisions, 1964-1981 (Box 70)
        - Drafts and revisions 1981-1984 (Box 71)
        - Drafts and revisions, 1984-1986 (Box 72)
        - Drafts, reprints and revisions, 1986-1997 (Box 73)
        - Faxes, drafts, prints and revisions, 1997-2001 (Box 74)
      - Maskin, E. (annotated papers and drafts on) (Box 74)
      - Monopoly - optimality, 2002 (Box 75)
      - Monopoly - non-optimality (Box 75)
      - Monopolistic Competition, 1970-1971 (Box 75)
      - "Effects of Entry On Profits Under Monopolistic Competition," 1986 (Box 75)
      - Monopolistic Competition, 1986-1988 (Box 76)
        - Various drafts and documents in relation with "effects of entry on profits under monopolistic competition" (Box 76)
      - Nakamura, Shinsuke (notes on), 1988-1996 (Box 76)
      - Nash Equilibrium
        - "On Cournot's solution of the Duopoly problem and the Nash Equilibrium Point," drafts and comments by Samuelson, includes a reprint of Nash, 1950, and bibliography (Box 76)
        - On attainable Nash equilibria, 1974, drafts and transparencies (Box 76)
        - Collaboration with Schmeidler, drafts and notes (Box 77)
        - Correspondence with JET in relation with "Attainable Nash equilibria," 1977 (Box 77)
        - Reprint, 1979 (Box 77)
        - McKenzie volume, Walrasian and Lindahl allocations at Nash Equilibrium, 1979 (Box 77)
        - Nash implementability, 1982 (Box 77)
        - James Jordan on Nash, 1998 (Box 78)
        - Walrasian and Lindahl allocations at Nash Equilibrium, feasible implentations, 1997-2001 (Box 78)
        - Nash Equilibrium, Miscellaneous, 1987-1990 (Box 78)
      - Public Goods (Hurwicz on), 1994 (Box 78)
      - Public Goods, Lindahl vs. Walrasian quadratics, 1979 (Box 78)
      - Radner and Reiter (works with), 1972 (Box 78)
      - Samuelson (article about and works by), 1964, 1970 (Box 78)
      - Shapiro (works in collaboration with), drafts, 1977 (Box 78)
      - Stability of General Equilibirum, 1957 (with Arrow), History (Box 78)
      - Reiter (H/R) and Reiter-Saari (H/R/S) Files, 1950s-2006, 23 boxes
        Hurwicz's collaboration with Stanley Reiter and Donald Saari represents a significant part of the Research and Writings Series. Spanning over three decades, those are very dense research materials including numerous projects, drafts, revisions, book chapters, proofs and presentations in seminars and conferences. The main output of this collaboration is Hurwicz and Reiter's Designing Economic Mechanisms, published in 2006. Preliminary work in relation with this book begins by 1978. Those papers are divided in two subseries: the Reiter collaboration and the HRS collaboration. HRS seems to be mostly a subdivision of the work by Hurwicz and Reiter, with added commentaries by Saari. Numerous drafts of book chapters with a similar aspect can be found with numerous annotations and subtle differences. One may find seemingly similar materials in the H/R files (11 boxes) on one hand and in the H/R/S files (12 boxes) on the other hand.
        The material, dealing with mechanism design, is heavily mathematical with an extensive use of geometric techniques - annotated reprints of Spivak's Differential Geometry are included. Recurring themes are the rectangle method and the condensation theorem. Beside collaborative works, these papers include other works by Reiter and Saari, with light annotations by Hurwicz and/or related correspondences. Each subseries is arranged in chronological order.
        - Reiter (Box 79)
          - Working papers by S. Reiter, 1950s (Box 79)
          - Reiter on Externalities, 1960s (Box 79)
          - "On the boundedness of feasible set ...," 1971 (Box 79)
          - Reiter on Informativeness, 1971 (Box 79)
          - Notes on Mount and Reiter, 1980-1983 (Box 79)
          - "Minimal decompositions," 1976 (Box 79)
          - Works done with Reiter in Evanston, 1979 (Box 79)
          - Page proofs, 1986 (Box 80)
          - NSF proposal, 1988 (Box 80)
          - Annotations on Walras (Box 80)
          - "Discrete Spaces," 1989 (Box 80)
          - "Rectangles," 1990 (Box 80)
          - Works on "Chapter 1" (untitled), several versions and revisions, 1992 (Box 81)
          - Reiter on "Discovery and Growth," 1993 (Box 81)
          - Mount and Reiter, 1995 (Box 82)
          - "Shoe Factory," 1995 (Box 82)
          - "Reverse Engineering," 1996 (Box 82)
          - Drafts, 1996 (Box 82)
          - "Constructing a special transversal," 1998 (Box 83)
          - Chapter II, Part A (on transversals) (Box 83)
          - Book project, 1998 (Box 83)
          - "Transversals and systems," 1998 (Box 83)
          - "Condensation," 1999 (Box 83)
          - "Condensation," various notes, memos and drafts (revisions) (Box 84)
          - Fax documents, 1999-2001 (Box 84)
          - "Flagpole Method," 1999-2000 (Box 85)
          - Transversals, 2000 (Box 85)
          - Various notes, memos and drafts (revisions) (Box 85)
          - Mount and Reiter, photocopies, 2001 (Box 85)
          - Various notes, memos and drafts (revisions) (Box 86)
          - Reprints, notes and faxes in preparation for the book Designing Economic Mechanisms, 2002-2004 (Box 86-88)
          - Cambridge University Press, correspondences about Designing Economic Mechanisms, 2004-2006 (Box 88)
          - Designing Economic Mechanisms, dust cover, 2006 (Box 88)
          - Various drafts by Reiter, 2004-2006 (Box 88)
          - Various arranged folders and thick binders, 1992-2004 (Box 89)
        - Reiter and Saari (Box 90)
          - Various drafts (Box 90)
          - Saari and Reiter on "separability," 1977 (Box 90)
          - On Constructing Mechanisms, draft, 1978 (Box 90)
          - Reprints (Box 90)
          - Various notes, drafts and reprints, 1978-1979 (Box 91)
          - Saari's corrections, 1979 (Box 92)
          - "Distribution of Differential Equations," 1980 (Box 92)
          - "The Riddle," 1980 (Box 92)
          - Chapter IV, Th. 6 and 7, notes (Box 92)
          - Steve William's comments, 1980 (Box 92)
          - "A Geometric Interpretation of the Integrability Conditions in Terms of Ideals," 1980 (Box 93)
          - Theorem 6 (Box 93)
          - Lemma A (Box 93)
          - Lemma B1, B2, B3 (Box 93)
          - "Separable performance functions" (Box 93)
          - "Walrasian Quadratic" (Box 93)
          - IMA Workshop (Box 93)
          - Part IV (Box 94)
          - Boulder, 1980 (Box 94)
          - Aix-en-Provence, 1980 (Box 94)
          - A thick folder with arranged documents (Box 94)
          - Shapiro's comments (Box 94)
          - Older versions (Box 94)
          - HRS, New Delhi, expository notes, 1981 (Box 94)
          - Saari review (Box 95)
          - Various works on transversals (construction, derivation), 1986 (Box 95)
          - Reiter, Oxford, 1987 (Box 96)
          - Transversal construction (Box 96)
          - Various drafts and notes (Box 96)
          - Various drafts and revisions on "transversals," 1987 (Box 97)
          - Chapter 1, revised (Box 97)
          - "On Modeling Institutions," New York AEA Meeting, 1988 (Box 98)
          - Various drafts and revisions (Box 98)
          - Inventory of papers (by topics), 1989-1990 (Box 98)
          - Perfect Product Structures (Box 99)
          - The Method of Rectangles (Box 99)
          - Chapter II (Box 99)
          - Part V (Box 99)
          - Miscellaneous papers, 1990-2003, accordion folder of drafts and reprints (Box 99)
          - Non-partitions (Box 100)
          - Various reprints (Box 100)
          - Miscellaneous papers (Box 100)
          - Spivak's Differential Geometry, book reprint with annotations (Box 101)
      - Marcel K. Richter Files, 1964-2001, 7 boxes
        Contains drafts and notes on collaborative work as well as reprints of Richter's writings with annotations by Hurwicz. Most of their collaboration took place in the 1990s and dealt with welfare economics. Arranged chronologically.
        - Reprints of Richter's articles and photocopies of Hurwicz's notes on Richter, 1960s (Box 101)
        - "Revealed Preference Theory," 1966 (Box 101)
        - "Social Choice, Competition and the Core," 1975 (Box 101)
        - Richter's notes on Nash Equilibrium, 1975 (Box 101)
        - Integrability, Journal of Mathematical Economics, 1979 (Box 101)
        - Richer's curriculum, 1984 (Box 101)
        - Richter on Public Goods, 1988 (Box 101)
        - A General Implicit Function Theorem, 1994 (Box 102)
        - Optimization and Lagrange Multipliers, 1996 (Box 102)
        - Works on the 2nd Welfare Theorem (Box 102)
        - Rational Choice by Richter, n.d. (Box 102)
        - "A note on the 2nd fundamental theorem of classical welfare economics," 1996 (Box 102)
        - Works on the 2nd Fundamental Welfare Theorem (Box 103)
        - Richter's vitae and various papers, 1998 (Box 103)
        - Various drafts and notes (Box 103)
        - "The Second fundamental theorem of classical welfare economics," multiple versions, 2000-2001 (Box 104)
        - Preliminary Thought on Disposability, 2001 (Box 104)
        - "Second Welfare Theorem," transparencies for presentation (Box 105)
        - "Lagrange Multipliers," transparencies (Box 105)
      - Uzawa, Hirofumi (collaboration), 1950s-1960s
        - Arrow, Hurwicz and Uzawa's Studies in Linear and Non-Linear Programming (in Russian), 1958 (Box 105)
        - The Integrability of Demand Functions (Box 105)
        - Asymptotic Production Sets (Box 105)
        - Correspondences and materials in relation with integrability (Box 105)
        - Uzawa, Hirofumi, post 1960s (Box 106)
        - Uzawa on the Integrability of Demand Functions, 1971 (Box 106)
        - Uzawa, Honolulu, 1980 (Box 106)
      - Varian, Hal, annotated works by, 1972-1977 (Box 106)
      - Weinberger, Hans, collaboration, 1985-1987 (Box 106)
      - Werner, Jan, collaboration, 1993-1995 (Box 106)
      - Werner on "Domain of Demand, The Minimum-Wealth Condition, The Existence of Competitive Equilibrium," 1995 (Box 107)
      - Steve Williams (annotated papers by), 1992-1996 (Box 107)
      - Williamson, Oliver (annotated papers), 1964-1981 (Box 107)
  - Various brochures
    - Congress (Box 42-43)
    - Economic Indicators (Box 42-43)
  - Works in Russian (papers and reprints) (Box 43)
  - Works in Russian (papers and reprints) (Box 44)
  - Books with annotations (Box 44A)
    - Arrow, Kenneth J., and F. H. Hahn, General Competitive Analysis. San Francisco: Holden-Day, Inc., 1971. (Box 44A)
    - Arrow, Kenneth J., and Leonid Hurwicz, Studies in resource allocation processes. 2nd ed. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1978. (Box 44A)
    - Baumol, William J., and Wallace E. Oates, The theory of environmental policy. 2nd ed. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1988. (Box 44A)
    - Eggertsson, Thrainn, Economic behavior and institutions. 2nd ed. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1991. (Box 44A)
    - Hildenbrand, Werner, Core and Equilibria of a Large Economy. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1974. (Box 44A)
    - Hildenbrand, W., and A. P. Kirman, Introduction to Equilibrium Analysis: Variations on themes by Edgeworth and Walras. New York: American Elsevier Publishing Co., Inc., 1976. (Box 44A)
  - Books with Annotations (Box 44B)
    - Karlin, Samuel, Mathematical Methods and Theory in Games, Programming, and Economics, Vol. I: Matrix Games, Programming, and Mathematical Economics. 2nd ed. Reading, M.A.: Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, Inc., 1962. (Box 44B)
    - Katzner, Donald M., Static Demand Theory. London: The MacMillan Company, 1970. (Box 44B)
    - Kolm, Serge-Christophe, La theorie des contraintes de valeur et ses applications. Paris: Dunod, 1970. (Box 44B)
    - Malinvaud, E., Lectures on Microeconomic Theory. Translated by Mrs. A. Silvey. New York: American Elsevier Publishing Co., Inc., 1969. (Box 44B)
    - Takayama, Akira, Mathematical economics. 2nd ed. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1985. (Box 44B)
- Professional Service Series, 1940s-2005, 12 boxes
  Documents Hurwicz's professional activities not directly related to research or teaching, such as research funding, publishing, Hurwicz's membership in various associations, participation on panels and committees, administrative tasks at the University of Minnesota, letters of recommendation, foreign travels, and speaking engagements. The materials cover most of Hurwicz's career with a stronger emphasis on activities after the 1980s. There are four subseries: Professional Activities by Subject (3.5 boxes), Letters of Recommendation (0.5 box), Foreign Travel (3 boxes) and Invited Talks (5 boxes).
  - Professional Activities by Subject
    - American Economic Association (Box 45)
    - American Academy of Arts and Science (Box 45)
    - ASSA Meeting, 2005 (Box 45)
    - Berkeley, 1976-77 (Box 45)
    - Cambridge University Press, 1987-8 (Box 45)
    - Chicago, 1940s (Box 45)
    - Chuo Research Unit for Global Environment (Box 45)
    - Cowles Commission (Box 45)
    - Doctoral Evaluation Program (Box 45)
    - Econometric Society, 1960s-1977 (Box 45)
    - Econometric Society 1977-2005 (Box 46)
    - France, 1981 (Box 46)
    - Harvard University, 1981 (Box 46)
    - International Economic Association (Box 46)
    - Indian Statistical Institute (Box 46)
    - Institute of Economics and Statistics (Box 46)
    - Journal of Comparative Economics (Box 46)
    - Metropolitan Transit Committee (Box 46)
    - Minnesota Academy of Science (Box 46)
    - Moscow Paper (Box 46)
    - National Academy of Science (Box 46)
    - National Medal of Science (Box 47)
    - NBER (National Bureau of Economic Research) (Box 47)
    - Nobel Prize, 1981 (Box 47)
    - Northwestern University (Box 47)
    - NSF (National Science Foundation) Proposals (Box 47)
    - NSF Applications (Box 47)
    - NSF Grants (Box 47)
    - NSF Fellowships (Box 47)
    - NSF Budget cuts, 1981 (Box 47)
    - Publishing - Book Projects, 1980s, 2 folders (Box 48)
    - Scientific American (Box 48)
    - Stanford University Press (Box 48)
    - University of Minnesota, 8 folders (Box 48)
    - Westview Press (Box 48)
  - Letters of Recommendation
    - Katzner (Box 48)
    - Manowski (Box 48)
    - Krisha (Box 48)
    - Bala (Box 48)
    - Postlewaite (Box 48)
    - Franck Page (Box 48)
    - Qi-Li (Box 48)
    - Béatrice Gaitan (Box 48)
    - Eward Schuh (Box 48)
    - Roswitha King (Box 48)
  - Foreign Travel
    - China, 1989-1990, 4 folders (Box 49)
    - Stockholm, 2 folders (Box 49)
    - Moscow, 1992, 5 folders (Box 49)
    - Japan, 1993-1999 (Box 49)
    - Spain (Box 49)
    - Greece (Box 50)
    - USSR, 1976 (Box 50)
    - Russian Trip (Box 50)
    - Korea, 1991 (Box 50)
    - USSR and various documents (Box 51)
  - Invited Talks
    - 1951-1974 (Box 51)
    - 1976-1988 (Box 52)
    - 1989-1997 (Box 53)
    - 1998-2000 (Box 54)
    - 1999-2001 (Box 55)
  - Various transparencies (Box 55-56)
- Research and Writings Series, 1911-2006 and undated, bulk 1945-2006, 142 boxes
  Represents approximately seventy percent of the collection. Contains notes, drafts, working papers, reprints, annotated manuscripts, faxes and letters related to Hurwicz's work as an economist. These papers span Hurwicz's entire career from his work with Kenneth Arrow and Hiro Uzawa at Cowles in the 1940s on the stability of general equilibrium and the integrability of demand functions, to his collaboration with Stanley Reiter on Designing Economic Mechanisms (2006).
  For the most part, Hurwicz's original arrangement and folder titles have been retained. The materials are ordered into two subseries: Topical and Other Research. Roughly half of the Research and Writings series (51 boxes) is arranged in a Topical Subseries. File folders represent either an important topic within Hurwicz's work or an extended collaboration with a colleague; there are also geographical files, including one on China. Within folders, materials are arranged in rough chronological order. There are also three boxes of correspondence related to works by others and seven boxes of unbound annotated works by others (in contrast with those included with the Printed Materials series, these are unbound and some are unpublished).
  Ninety-one other boxes in the Other Research Subseries contain files that have retained their original order as received by the library and have been given basic processing and arrangement. The descriptions are broad, with significant topics or individuals highlighted; not all folders are represented. There are a number of files related to geographical headings, especially relating to the economies of the former Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, and in smaller degree to Poland and New Zealand. Hurwicz also was interested in refugees and public policy, and this is reflected by folders of material on that subject.
  - Other Research and Writings Subseries, 1911-2004 and undated, bulk 1945-2004, 91 boxes
    Chiefly consists of Hurwicz's research notes and drafts relating to projects and collaborations; correspondence folders; reprints, articles, and other writings by other economists, scientists, and students; conference records; and other mixed papers. May also contain some personal papers and teaching materials. Early dates refer chiefly to reprints and articles, often accompanied by Hurwicz's notes on those early works. Topics covered by research notes and other materials vary, but focus chiefly on mathematical equations and modeling for institutional change, equilibrium, mechanism design, convergence, and condensation. There are many folders with materials relating to Hurwicz's collaborations with Stan Reiter. At least several folders of materials from the 1990s and early 2000s focus on Indian, Eastern European and Russian economic changes.
    - Research notes, drafts and published articles by Hurwicz and others (Box 108)
      - Resource allocation, 1978-1985 (Box 108)
      - Decentralization, 1981 (Box 108)
      - Nash equilibrium (with Arrow) (Box 108)
      - Incentive structures and maximizing residual gain, 1977-1981 (Box 108)
      - Institutions and institutional change, 1987-1990 (Box 108)
      - Linear and non-linear programming (with Arrow and Uzawa), 1958-1986 (Box 108)
    - Notes, photocopied publications by others, drafts, and project collaborations (Box 109)
      - Discrete allocation mechanisms with Marschak, 1981-1985, 3 folders (Box 109)
      - Constructing mechanisms with message spaces, with Reiter and Saari, 1978 (Box 109)
      - Decentralization (Box 109)
      - Saddle points, with Arrow (Box 109)
    - Notes and drafts, Hurwicz and others (Box 110)
      - Perspectives on economics, New Orleans, 1976 (Box 110)
      - Economic impact of ISPAs, 1976 (Box 110)
      - Imperfect markets with free entry, 1979 (Box 110)
      - Socialism and incentives (Box 110)
      - Reiter, notes and original work on efficient allocation, equilibria, 1970s-1980s (Box 110)
    - Notes, printed work of others, and correspondence (Box 111)
      - Teaching notes, 1998 (Box 111)
      - Incentive compatibility, 1974 (Box 111)
      - Miscellaneous notes on equilibria, Walrasian models, optimality mechanisms, 11 folders (Box 111)
      - Printed articles (Box 111)
      - Centralized and decentralized structures, 1958 and undated (Box 111)
      - Maximizing life savings, work by others (Box 111)
    - Notes, papers, presentation materials, and others' manuscripts (Box 112)
      - Cost-benefit analysis: willingness to pay vs. value of life; auto industry; air pollution, etc., 1997 (Box 112)
      - Designing mechanisms, 1995 (Box 112)
      - Transversals, rectification, and equilibrium, 1990 (Box 112)
      - Fluoridation (Box 112)
      - Adjustment processes, 1955 (Box 112)
      - Stability of competitive equilibrium, 1958-1959 (draft) (Box 112)
      - Bivariate normal, 1950s (notes) (Box 112)
      - Weather modification report, National Science Foundation, 1965 (Box 112)
      - Cores and competitive equilibria in discrete spaces, 1992 (Box 112)
    - Notes, collaborations,and original work (Box 113)
      - Various notes, transparencies, and miscellaneous documents, 15 folders (Box 113)
      - Reiter, Arrow, and Marschak collaborations (Box 113)
      - Integrability of Demand Functions, with Uzawa, 1971 (Box 113)
      - Decision and organization, with Marschak, 1971 (Box 113)
      - Manuscripts and publications by Hurwicz and others, 1951-1984 (Box 113)
      - Fix-Point Theorem with Econometric Background, draft by H. Wold, 1964 (Box 113)
    - Notes, collaborations and correspondence (Box 114)
      - Notes and drafts on optimality, discrete spaces (Box 114)
      - Collaboration with Marschak, 1979-1982 (Box 114)
        Includes correspondence from Marschak on informational size of discrete spaces.
      - Thomson, Linear Utilities (Box 114)
      - Teaching material, 1975-1983 (Box 114)
      - Collaborations with Arrow, resource allocation and others, 1959, 1982 and undated (Box 114)
      - Correspondence, 1979-1981, 14 folders (Box 114)
        With Reiter, Marschak, and others.
      - Hurwicz/Maskin/Postlewaite collaboration, 1979-1982 (Box 114)
    - Letters, meetings, notes, diagrams, drafts, and publications by others (Box 115)
      - Correspondence, 1950-1964 (Box 115)
      - Sharecropper problem (notes), 2 folders (Box 115)
      - Reiter, "Organization Theory," 1955 and undated (Box 115)